This material is made available to you by or on
NOTE CONF
behalf of the University of Melbourne under section 113P of
the Copyright Act 1968.
NOTE CONF
It may be subject to copyright.
For more information, visit the university copyright website.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Uh, welcome, everyone.
NOTE CONF
Week 2.
Got quite a bit of material to get through.
NOTE CONF
I had a question that I left you with last
week, which I hope you've been thinking about all weekend.
NOTE CONF
I'm sure you've got.
Better things to do, but maybe spend some time thinking
NOTE CONF
about the question and I'm gonna bring up that question
again and see how many people have an answer for
NOTE CONF
it in a moment, while let's start with uh what
we're doing this week.
NOTE CONF
So the recommended sequence of things that you might do
is to start, of course, with the material module two,
NOTE CONF
which is online.
Um, I'm assuming nobody's got any issues with getting on
NOTE CONF
to the LMS and Uh, going through the, the content
that is structured online for easy learning.
NOTE CONF
Uh, the textbook, How many of you have purchased the
textbook?
NOTE CONF
Oh dear.
Um, OK, fantastic.
NOTE CONF
2 people.
Wonderful.
NOTE CONF
The publisher sent me an email saying, hey, we're giving
you 10% discount if you buy directly from us.
NOTE CONF
I've put that up on the textbook page.
Uh, so you can go to the LMS, uh, site,
NOTE CONF
go to the page where we, we actually prescribe, we
have the details of the textbook, and you'll see a
NOTE CONF
little poster there with a 10% discount coupon if you're
interested in buying from C Engage directly, right?
NOTE CONF
Uh, so read the textbook, please.
Uh, and then number 3, answer discussion questions that are
NOTE CONF
on the Canvas site.
I know I've seen some people have started answering questions,
NOTE CONF
which is fantastic.
Uh, please build your community there, have conversations there, and
NOTE CONF
if you come up with Questions that you simply have
you're struggling to to answer, refer them to your tutor,
NOTE CONF
refer them to me.
the workshop in this subject, we use tutorial workshop interchangeably.
NOTE CONF
So this is the first week of 2 hour workshops.
We're trying to open more classes because I think there
NOTE CONF
are, there are only at the moment 123 classes open,
and I'm trying to get the school to open more
NOTE CONF
classrooms and we'll schedule them hopefully at the same time
that the existing classes run, so.
NOTE CONF
Uh, you won't have to rejig your timetable.
We can simply reduce the size of some of these
NOTE CONF
classes, which is what I'd like to do.
Uh, but yeah, so this week, uh, you have your
NOTE CONF
first two-hour workshops, please show up.
Uh, please come prepared, uh, read the Fitzgerald, uh, paper.
NOTE CONF
It's not very long, it's very short, but you need
to understand that paper to be able to do the
NOTE CONF
activity, which is the, in the second half of the
Of the two-hour workshop.
NOTE CONF
So the, the workshop will be structured into 3 pieces.
First of all, there'll be a Q&A on the week's
NOTE CONF
content.
Uh, the, the tutor might go through some of the
NOTE CONF
highlights from the tutor's perspective, um, and then, uh, taking
questions from you, of course, and then into the roleplay
NOTE CONF
activity, which will be around, uh, understanding the different perspectives
of CEOs, CIOs, and CISOs.
NOTE CONF
Uh, this week's learning objectives, understand the significance of the
triplet model.
NOTE CONF
This is the core.
The core model that, that drives the engine for the
NOTE CONF
whole subject, um, identify, described role of information security, protecting
information resources, understand the responsibilities and key function of the
NOTE CONF
chief information security officer within an organization, and hopefully I'll
be able to go through these three today.
NOTE CONF
So, starting again with the same quote that we started
with last week.
NOTE CONF
If you think technology can solve your security problems, and
you don't understand the problems and you don't understand technology,
NOTE CONF
when I asked you last week why you thought this
might be true, the answers I gave were all around,
NOTE CONF
hey, we should use technology better.
It's not technology's fault.
NOTE CONF
All the time, sometimes it's the human's fault, and although
that is true, that is not what we were talking
NOTE CONF
about, right?
So that is true.
NOTE CONF
It's not to say that risks don't emerge from the
human use of technology, but what we're saying is that
NOTE CONF
information resources, these assets that we're trying to protect in
an organization, some of them do not exist within the
NOTE CONF
digital environment at all.
So this line.
NOTE CONF
is talking about the scope of information security being too
narrowly focused on digital platforms and the use of digital
NOTE CONF
platforms and more broader needs to speak to paper information
and what's going on in people's heads, which is a
NOTE CONF
much broader problem than what people normally assume when they
talk about cybersecurity or information security, and we like to
NOTE CONF
use those two.
Phrases interchangeably.
NOTE CONF
So I had 3 questions last week, and we, we
stopped at the 3rd 1.
NOTE CONF
You remember the T-Mobile versus Huawei scenario?
Yeah?
NOTE CONF
OK.
So, what did T-Mobile not do that they should have
NOTE CONF
done to address the challenge of IP theft from Huawei,
the alleged, just kidding, right, IP theft from Huawei.
NOTE CONF
What did they not do?
And I gave you a very strong hint last week.
NOTE CONF
The answer is not a piece of technology.
It's not more biometrics, it's not.
NOTE CONF
You know it's not some kind of high tech.
Operational solution It's not an operational solution at all, right?
NOTE CONF
So, What are you guys thinking?
Has, has anybody come up with something they'd like to
NOTE CONF
try out?
Maybe they just.
NOTE CONF
I go to.
Uh, that's what, what, what, what should T-Mobile have done
NOTE CONF
that they didn't do when they protect they were setting
up their design of the security of their, their mobile
NOTE CONF
phone testing robot.
What did they not do?
NOTE CONF
That is the question.
OK.
NOTE CONF
It's a high security environment, right?
They had guards posted outside.
NOTE CONF
They had biometrics.
They had they had all your cyber technologies, well, whatever
NOTE CONF
you could put in that environment, access control technologies in
the environment already.
NOTE CONF
They had already trained their people on how to manage
the security of the environment around the robot, and yet
NOTE CONF
this happened.
What is the problem?
NOTE CONF
Yes.
The data, the data itself, are we talking about the
NOTE CONF
software that's running the robot that they stole?
The data that is being captured by Thank.
NOTE CONF
How that So, so what, what Huawei is, is alleged
to have done is to have taken photographs, right?
NOTE CONF
Taking a piece of the actual robot.
Taken the software, asked inappropriate questions.
NOTE CONF
That's how they, that's how they, they, T-Mobile alleges they
managed to steal the robot, right?
NOTE CONF
So obviously they didn't take the whole robot and run
off with it.
NOTE CONF
They were already trying to build one.
They couldn't crack the, the puzzle, so the parts that
NOTE CONF
they couldn't figure out, they addressed those by doing this.
Everybody agreed that this was a cybersecurity incident, or most
NOTE CONF
people I think agreed last week, this was a cybersecurity
incident.
NOTE CONF
So why aren't the cybersecurity controls working?
Yes, I feel like they underestimated how easy it would
NOTE CONF
be to piece together what, what like the proprietary information
from all of the different parts that they so they
NOTE CONF
didn't see.
That's, that's a really good insight.
NOTE CONF
That's a great insight, right, because when you're building your
security strategy, you're thinking, oh, I'm protecting A, B, C,
NOTE CONF
D.
You're not thinking about the bits and pieces that somebody
NOTE CONF
can actually collect about you.
And piece together in another organization because you don't know
NOTE CONF
what they know about you, you don't know what they
need, and you're not looking at their, you know, at
NOTE CONF
their motivation, their intention, you're just looking at the whole
asset and saying don't, you know, protect the asset as
NOTE CONF
a whole.
You're not actually protecting yourself from the perspective of an
NOTE CONF
adversary, what they're doing.
So what should they have done?
NOTE CONF
So that's a great insight.
The next question is, so what's the strategy?
NOTE CONF
What is the strategy This is the type of question
you're gonna get on your exam.
NOTE CONF
And this is the kind of response we got last
year in the exam.
NOTE CONF
Right, with the most students looking at the, the case
analysis and just bombing out like no idea what to
NOTE CONF
say, right?
They, I can't believe they went through the entire subject
NOTE CONF
where that's preaching, cyber is not a technology problem, and
a lot of the answers we got is encryption, you
NOTE CONF
know, like all the stuff we say is not, is
not what we want you to think.
NOTE CONF
All those things came out, yeah, policies that prevent things
from happening.
NOTE CONF
They already have the policies.
Prevent what from happening?
NOTE CONF
OK, but you put those policies in, they won't take
pictures.
NOTE CONF
They'll do something else.
You're not dealing with the strategic challenge.
NOTE CONF
You're dealing operationally with the, oh, they took notes, stopped
notes, photos, so they'll do something different.
NOTE CONF
Can you isolate the intellectual property?
It's embedded in the, in the robot.
NOTE CONF
And you have to give access to the robot, otherwise
your partners can go in and test their phones.
NOTE CONF
OK, we don't have a whole lot of time to,
to discuss.
NOTE CONF
I'm just gonna tell you what I would do.
This is not the solution, this is what I would
NOTE CONF
do, OK?
And from the purpose, from the point of view of
NOTE CONF
the subject, this is what we want, this is how
we want you to think.
NOTE CONF
Number 1, when T-Mobile went into partnership with Huawei, the
first thing they should have done is they should have
NOTE CONF
done a study of Huawei's track record, right?
Huawei has a track record of taking IP.
NOTE CONF
Right.
Now, knowing that is the kind of organization they're dealing
NOTE CONF
with, going into a business partnership with an organization that
has a history of doing that, the first thing you
NOTE CONF
would do is set up a team whose job it
is to monitor Huawei's behavior.
NOTE CONF
Right.
So, they're acting like a business partner, but tomorrow they
NOTE CONF
might turn into a competitor.
So what would they do?
NOTE CONF
If they were a competitor and they wanted to take
something from us, first thing, second thing you do after
NOTE CONF
setting up the team is figuring out what is Huawei
doing at the moment in the mobile phone area.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, what kinds of phones are they building?
What is their strategic motivation?
NOTE CONF
What is, what are they trying to do with themselves
as a company?
NOTE CONF
As soon as you realize that, hey, they have the
same problem that we have, which is the deficient phones,
NOTE CONF
they're most likely, if we were them, we would want
to build a mobile phone robot like ours, right?
NOTE CONF
OK, let's assume they're trying to build one.
What do you think they need from us that they
NOTE CONF
would take?
Now, as soon as you are at that level where
NOTE CONF
you go, oh, the most expected behavioral pattern is for
them to switch from partner to competitor, you would start
NOTE CONF
monitoring their behavior and as soon as they ask the
first question, the inappropriate question, you would realize, uh, that
NOTE CONF
they've now shifted to competitor.
We need to cut off the entire organization and cut
NOTE CONF
off those people who already have access to us, right,
because now they've switched from partner to competitor.
NOTE CONF
Now, if you do that, you cut off access, that's
the end of that organization's ability to penetrate your firm
NOTE CONF
from the inside, not talking about external attacks, insider attacks
gone.
NOTE CONF
This problem That we're talking about is solved at a
strategic level by an organization that is able to understand
NOTE CONF
its threat environment and to extrapolate the behavior of all
those entities that it, that's in its ecosystem, right?
NOTE CONF
This is what you do.
This is what threat intel is all about.
NOTE CONF
You have to collect threat intelligence about not only those
threat actors that are attacking your firm, but your business
NOTE CONF
partners who might turn into competitors.
That threat intel will tell you.
NOTE CONF
How to understand the behavior of the people around you,
which no operational technology will solve, right?
NOTE CONF
Operational technology only works if you know what you're looking
for.
NOTE CONF
If you don't know what you're looking for, it's not
going to help you.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
So the strategy here is threat intel, building the monitoring
NOTE CONF
capability, asking the questions, thinking adversarially, and then playing that
behavior out and saying, where are we gonna see that
NOTE CONF
behavior in the firm, and then As soon as that
behavior shows up, it triggers your security response, right?
NOTE CONF
So how do you trigger your security response?
You trigger it by understanding what are the behaviors you're
NOTE CONF
looking for, which only makes sense from a strategic point
of view, not from an operational point of view.
NOTE CONF
So you can sit there in the clean room watching
people go in and out every day, and you won't
NOTE CONF
know the difference between somebody who's a partner and somebody
who's a threat actor.
NOTE CONF
Yes.
Companies like T-Mobile and I have an MOU in place
NOTE CONF
before they do anything, what's the value of the MOU?
It's not worth the paper it's on.
NOTE CONF
Right?
How many legal cases have you heard of where an
NOTE CONF
MOU breach has resulted in a conviction of anything?
MOUs are more dangerous than not having them, because when
NOTE CONF
you sign an MOU, organizations, they drop their defenses.
Oh, we have an MOU now we can speak freely.
NOTE CONF
No, you can't, right?
MOUs are not worth it.
NOTE CONF
And the problem when you're pursuing a company that's not
in your country, that's in another country that doesn't follow
NOTE CONF
your legal jurisdiction, is that you can't pursue them there.
Right?
NOTE CONF
So this is another reason why there was, there's no
legal recourse when you've got international trade going on, and
NOTE CONF
people are actually taking from each other, and they live
in different legal jurisdictions, you can't chase them.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
So yeah, you would think, hey, can we sue them?
NOTE CONF
Good luck.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
OK.
We need to move really quickly on a whole range
NOTE CONF
of topics.
This is a really important slide again.
NOTE CONF
This is called, this is sort of an iceberg type
model.
NOTE CONF
Um, what it's basically saying here, I don't think you
can read the text from the back.
NOTE CONF
What it's basically saying here is that when you have
cyber incident in your company, there are certain impacts that
NOTE CONF
you expect.
For example, you'll have a technical investigation that you'll have
NOTE CONF
to do.
You might have to notify customers that have been affected
NOTE CONF
by the breach.
How many of you were affected by the Optus breach
NOTE CONF
some years ago?
Nobody has an Optus account that was, you know, the
NOTE CONF
driver's license was taken out, but maybe you guys haven't
been here that long.
NOTE CONF
I don't know.
Um, but when Optus had just breached 9 million customers,
NOTE CONF
they had to issue new driver's licenses for all of
them with a new number, not your normal driver's license
NOTE CONF
number, but a secondary number.
Yeah, and who paid for that?
NOTE CONF
Optus paid for it.
Well, Singapore, Singtel, right?
NOTE CONF
But I mean, the, the point here is that Massive
costs, right?
NOTE CONF
So customer breach notification and then after the breach has
been addressed, post breach management protection, attorney fees and litigation.
NOTE CONF
Why do you need lawyers?
Because you need to speak to the media, cybersecurity improvements,
NOTE CONF
regulatory compliance, these are things that everybody expects.
Then below the surface of all the things you don't
NOTE CONF
expect, for example, Your insurance premium increases.
For example, you want to take out a loan, the
NOTE CONF
cost of taking out a loan increases.
You have your long term operational disruption which can go
NOTE CONF
on on the right hand side.
Business recovery can take up to 5 years after a
NOTE CONF
major breach.
But more than all of that is devaluation of your
NOTE CONF
trade name and loss of trust with your customers, right?
Once you've had a major breach, Then your customers begin
NOTE CONF
to not trust you, and to rebuild that trust can
take a very, very long time, and it is extremely
NOTE CONF
costly.
That most corporations that suffer in a cyber attack, a
NOTE CONF
breach, do not actually consider that cost in their calculations.
So the point of this particular diagram is to say
NOTE CONF
that 95% of the cost of a cyber attack is
unexpected, and it doesn't just take a couple of days
NOTE CONF
or a couple of weeks, it can take years.
OK.
NOTE CONF
This is the main model for the whole course.
So please pay attention to this one, OK.
NOTE CONF
This model comes from security science, not from computer science,
and it basically says that if you ever are in
NOTE CONF
a situation where you don't understand what is going on
from a security point of view, this is your North
NOTE CONF
Star.
This will help you to frame the security problem very
NOTE CONF
accurately, very precisely.
And it basically says this, if you, for there to
NOTE CONF
be a security problem, you have to have two things.
Number 1, you have to have an asset, something that
NOTE CONF
needs to be protected, something that's got value for you,
and there's got to be a threat.
NOTE CONF
An asset and the threat are the two ingredients that
make a security problem, something that's worth protecting and something
NOTE CONF
that you have to protect that thing from.
Threat actor or threat asset.
NOTE CONF
You need these two ingredients for there to be a
security problem.
NOTE CONF
If there is nothing worth protecting, there's no security problem.
If you have something worth protecting, but there's no danger
NOTE CONF
to it, there's no security problem.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Two things.
An asset and a threat.
NOTE CONF
Now, in order to actually address or understand security, we
need to figure out what are the possible ways that
NOTE CONF
a threat actor or a threat can reach an asset,
and that's usually best described as a scenario, right?
NOTE CONF
So when a threat actor exploits a vulnerability in an
asset to create an impact, that's usually one risk.
NOTE CONF
A specific threat actor exploits a specific vulnerability in a
specific asset to create an impact.
NOTE CONF
The impact is not specific.
Could be general or specific, right?
NOTE CONF
So you need this, this combination of three specific things,
a very specific asset, very specific threat, very specific vulnerability
NOTE CONF
that's been exploited, and that combination.
Creates a risk for your organization that you need to
NOTE CONF
address.
Now, in an organization, there might be a lot of
NOTE CONF
assets.
Hint IT is not an asset in this context.
NOTE CONF
IT is too big, right, to be called an asset.
Your email service is an asset, your database service is
NOTE CONF
an asset, your web service is an asset, your e-commerce
service is an asset.
NOTE CONF
Every document that is sensitive in your organization is an
asset.
NOTE CONF
Every individual who has unique expertise that pro that is
provided into organization to create value.
NOTE CONF
is an asset.
How many assets might there be in an organization?
NOTE CONF
A lot In a multinational organization, 1000s, 100,000s.
How many threat actors are there?
NOTE CONF
A lot.
How many combinations of, how many vulnerabilities might there be
NOTE CONF
in one asset?
A lot.
NOTE CONF
So the combination of every asset, and every vulnerability in
that asset, and every threat and the pathway, the collective
NOTE CONF
pathway, there are a lot of scenarios that could end
up badly for your firm.
NOTE CONF
Hundreds of thousands of them.
So security then becomes this very specific problem.
NOTE CONF
Security management becomes how I know that there are a
lot of assets, a lot of scenarios and I need
NOTE CONF
to identify them, but I can never reduce the risks,
the scenarios to zero.
NOTE CONF
And I don't have an unlimited budget.
So, how can I best use my resources?
NOTE CONF
To find that balance, right?
Where I use my budget to reduce the risk exposure
NOTE CONF
to a level that I can accept, right?
So that means I identify the scenarios, I figure out
NOTE CONF
what is the risk exposure for each one of them,
we'll talk about that later.
NOTE CONF
And collectively, my risk profile is the collection of all
the risk that comes from all the scenarios.
NOTE CONF
Right, that's my risk exposure.
All the risk that comes from all these scenarios is
NOTE CONF
my exposure, and I've got a budget.
What will I do with the, with my budget to
NOTE CONF
try to reduce that risk exposure by putting in controls.
Reduce, reduce, reduce, reduce, and if I use my budget
NOTE CONF
intelligently, leverage my budget to its best advantage, I might
be able to reduce my risk to a level that
NOTE CONF
I can accept.
Right, and we call that risk appetite.
NOTE CONF
What is your risk appetite?
How much risk can you accept?
NOTE CONF
You cannot go to zero, you do not have an
unlimited budget.
NOTE CONF
So what is risk security management, you know, become?
It becomes finding that balance, right?
NOTE CONF
The balance is, how much money, how much, how much
resources do I have?
NOTE CONF
How much risk can I reduce?
Where, you know, where is the balance between my expenditure
NOTE CONF
and my reduction?
I need to find what is, what is an acceptable
NOTE CONF
amount of risk reduction because I can't go to zero,
right?
NOTE CONF
That is the balance that we're always seeking.
And when you start off as a security manager, you
NOTE CONF
don't know where that balance is.
You're struggling to find that balance, but ultimately over years,
NOTE CONF
you begin to recognize that your resources can be used
to reduce your risk to a certain level, and yeah,
NOTE CONF
you might still get attacked, but you always make this
calculated decision about how much risk I can absorb in
NOTE CONF
this firm.
That is what it's about, and you're, you're going to
NOTE CONF
be fundamentally different from the firefighter who does no calculation
and just goes, oh, I got an incident, I'll deal
NOTE CONF
with it and another one and another one, another one,
and they have no clue, they just keep spending money.
NOTE CONF
It's like a black hole.
They have no idea where the balance is, right?
NOTE CONF
So you have two security.
One that's a firefighter that has no risk calculation in
NOTE CONF
their mind.
They just do whatever makes sense in the moment.
NOTE CONF
And then you have the security manager who is the
strategist whose entire job is to say, I can't do
NOTE CONF
everything.
What can I do to my best advantage and find
NOTE CONF
that nice balance.
That is the balance that we seek in security management,
NOTE CONF
and that's what the triplet model directs us to.
Never start thinking about security till you know what you're
NOTE CONF
protecting, right?
Figuring out what is the value of what you're protecting,
NOTE CONF
how much are you gonna spend to protect it?
The amount that you can spend, what controls can you
NOTE CONF
buy for it?
The best people, the best technology, the best processes, put
NOTE CONF
them in place, find how much risk you've reduced, and
then sleep on that, right?
NOTE CONF
And keep refining, refining, refining until you find that that's
a good balance.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Now, I've got to switch to this particular very important
NOTE CONF
slide, which says there are 3 types of assets in
an organization.
NOTE CONF
I'm not saying there are 3 assets, there are 3
categories of assets.
NOTE CONF
So when you're looking for an asset, and you're saying,
what's an asset?
NOTE CONF
We expect you to start with the bottom, digital platforms.
Every digital platform is an asset.
NOTE CONF
No problem there.
You go around hunting with your virtual magnifying glass, and
NOTE CONF
you find all the assets that exist in your firm.
You've got a list of all the digital platforms, no
NOTE CONF
problem.
Right.
NOTE CONF
Then, The second category is information.
Right.
NOTE CONF
Data slash information, another category of assets, and here's where
the problem starts, because you realize that there is so
NOTE CONF
much information in your organization that's circulating that you have
no control over and actually the amount of information you're
NOTE CONF
ingesting as a firm through your emails, through whatever ways
that information comes into your organizations, social media, whatever, and
NOTE CONF
the amount of information that you are vomiting back out
into the world.
NOTE CONF
All of that input, output, and circulation is so large,
it's like an ocean, and information moves like ocean currents
NOTE CONF
move.
How am I going to possibly grapple with that amount
NOTE CONF
of information?
That is a problem for sure.
NOTE CONF
But your problem is not to deal with all of
it, but to figure out what's important in that information,
NOTE CONF
what is sensitive and needs protection, and that's not usually
all of it, that might be 1% of it.
NOTE CONF
Or 2%, right?
But the problem you're going to have if you walk
NOTE CONF
into an organization and ask these questions, is most organizations
are uncomfortable with these questions, because it opens up a
NOTE CONF
Pandora's box for them.
When you talk about information, are we talking about information
NOTE CONF
only in the digital environment?
What about paper?
NOTE CONF
What about those half copied pieces of paper on the
photocopier, right?
NOTE CONF
What about, you know, every chunk of every paragraph that
gets posted into social media or my email?
NOTE CONF
Like, what do I do with all of this information?
Yeah, that's a problem.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, but that is your second category.
You need to know what assets, what documents, what information
NOTE CONF
needs to be protected.
And then the 3rd, you may never have heard of.
NOTE CONF
How many, how many of you have done knowledge management?
As a subject.
NOTE CONF
At the university.
Yeah, no, OK.
NOTE CONF
So, maybe people don't know what knowledge is.
So you've heard of data.
NOTE CONF
You know what data is, right?
And then you've heard information.
NOTE CONF
What's the difference between data and information?
Data is unstructured.
NOTE CONF
So data is like raw raw figures, right, that have
no meaning to them.
NOTE CONF
A, B, 12, 10, whatever, but when you give context
to it, like, for example, 10 ft is the length
NOTE CONF
of the table, uh, you know, one side of the
table, that's information.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
So, there's data, there's information, then there's knowledge.
NOTE CONF
What's knowledge?
One person said he did subject in knowledge management.
NOTE CONF
What's knowledge?
Hard to define.
NOTE CONF
Information when you actually make use of it and you
combine it with your expertise and your judgment and you
NOTE CONF
put it to use to make value, right?
That's knowledge.
NOTE CONF
And there are two types of knowledge that we need
to be aware of, tacit knowledge and explicit knowledge.
NOTE CONF
And this is very important from a security point of
view.
NOTE CONF
And my best example is my MasterChef example to try
to illustrate this, right?
NOTE CONF
I didn't make up the example.
It's a very, it's a classic example from knowledge management
NOTE CONF
studies.
Everybody knows what a MasterChef is, yes?
NOTE CONF
OK.
A master chef.
NOTE CONF
Uh, basically, is usually known for their expertise in cooking
and particularly their signature dishes.
NOTE CONF
Everybody knows that a master chef has a signature dish.
Now, if you were a working hand, you know, you
NOTE CONF
know, you know your way around the kitchen, and you
go to a master chef, you say, Master chef, I
NOTE CONF
love this amazing dish that you make.
I want you to write down the recipe for this
NOTE CONF
dish, right?
Very detailed recipe.
NOTE CONF
So, How much, you know, of each, what ingredients did
you use, how much of each ingredient?
NOTE CONF
Where did you get them from?
How did you combine them, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
you know, the full recipe, even a video of them
NOTE CONF
doing it.
Now, let me ask you this question, if you were
NOTE CONF
that working hand and you try to follow that recipe,
exactly would you be able to reproduce that dish?
NOTE CONF
No.
Absolutely not, because there's something missing in that equation, which
NOTE CONF
is that MasterChef's experience, their judgment, their muscle memory, um,
the years and years that they've put into refining, which
NOTE CONF
you simply cannot copy by simply following instructions.
Try it.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, and that's one reason why, uh, master chefs don't
get made in lecture theaters.
NOTE CONF
You don't learn cooking in lecture theaters, you learn it
by apprenticeship, yeah.
NOTE CONF
You don't learn martial arts in a lecture theater, you
learn in a gym, yeah.
NOTE CONF
There are a lot of these professions that are not
taught in universities because you cannot transfer knowledge simply by
NOTE CONF
speaking.
You need to demonstrate and demonstrate and demonstrate for years
NOTE CONF
to refine the behavior, right?
That's kind of what master chefs do.
NOTE CONF
Now, the difference between tacit and explicit is the knowledge
that they could not tell you, but is bound to
NOTE CONF
who they are is tacit knowledge.
Explicit knowledge is everything that you could write down even
NOTE CONF
by asking them questions.
So bringing this back into security in pharmaceutical firms, for
NOTE CONF
instance, or advanced manufacturing firms Ferrari, Lamborghini, all these big
companies or aircraft manufacturing Boeing, Airbus, or you could even
NOTE CONF
say software companies Google, Microsoft, etc.
they've got these MasterChef type people whose job it is.
NOTE CONF
Bring together all these ingredients to make the product that
the organization is known for, right?
NOTE CONF
in advanced manufacturing, like in these, these supercar companies, it's
the, you know, it's how they use their carbon fiber,
NOTE CONF
how they mold their carbon fiber.
It's the high performance engines and their propulsion and their
NOTE CONF
weight to performance ratio and all of the very special
expertise that exists in the organization.
NOTE CONF
In the people and that expertise, how it gets translated
into building unique tools that only that organization has, the
NOTE CONF
way they do their testing, the way they do their
quality assurance, it's unique to the organization, it's their, their
NOTE CONF
super secret trade secrets that they don't want anybody to
know, right?
NOTE CONF
And we drink them every day Pepsi, Coke, the recipe
for them, KFC.
NOTE CONF
They're all closely guarded secrets because they know that if
a competitor gets hold of them, not just the recipe,
NOTE CONF
but the ability to use the recipe to manufacture and
to replicate their capability.
NOTE CONF
They will be kicked out of their entire industry, right?
You cannot survive.
NOTE CONF
You can survive a cyberattack on your network and bring
your network back up.
NOTE CONF
You can probably survive if information leaves your organization, right?
Some information, but your recipe, you lose your recipe, your
NOTE CONF
company is finished.
Yeah, it's the secret ingredient to the company's success.
NOTE CONF
It's the crown jewels, and from a security point of
view, it's what we need to be protecting.
NOTE CONF
Right?
But we're not usually.
NOTE CONF
Why?
Because of the, these three types of assets, the trade
NOTE CONF
secret knowledge asset exists in few firms, not in every
firm.
NOTE CONF
Well, you could argue trade secrets or expertise exists in
most firms, but the firms that will die if they
NOTE CONF
get stolen are not that many, and you might not
encounter them unless you work for a pharmaceutical firm or
NOTE CONF
advanced manufacturing firm.
You may not encounter them.
NOTE CONF
So you might think, having worked in a bank or
a telco, that I know what cyber is like, but
NOTE CONF
you know what, cyber looks very different in a pharmaceutical
firm.
NOTE CONF
security looks different.
They're training the scientists in the labs to speak languages
NOTE CONF
that other scientists don't understand because they're trying to control
and compartmentalize and build confidentiality bubbles around scientists, because if
NOTE CONF
the trials get contaminated, they'll lose billions of dollars worth
of investment, right?
NOTE CONF
So the types of security you see in pharmaceutical firms
doesn't look anything like a bank, right.
NOTE CONF
And the reason why I'm telling you all this because
as security people, people who are trained to be security
NOTE CONF
experts, you need to know the vast breadth of it,
not just the, you know, the, the easy part or
NOTE CONF
the part that's most common.
You need to see the whole breadth of what the
NOTE CONF
security problem looks like.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Why do organizations get attacked?
For many reasons.
NOTE CONF
Because somebody wants to replicate their capability, because somebody wants
to lock them out of their own IT, right, ransomware,
NOTE CONF
and then ransom them for it, extortion, uh, because they
want information that the organization holds but may not even
NOTE CONF
realize is valuable, right?
So many organizations hold information that belongs to somebody else,
NOTE CONF
but they don't know the value of it, so they
don't protect it.
NOTE CONF
Because of trust relationships, you might not be an attacker
might not be able to get into the firm they're
NOTE CONF
targeting, but that firm has a trust relationship with somebody
else with a low level of risk, security, and they
NOTE CONF
can attack them and go through that pathway, which is
why nowadays you know supply chain risk and third party
NOTE CONF
risk is all the rage, right, because the organizations begin
to realize that there are so many ways into our
NOTE CONF
firm, not just the front door.
There's the side door and the back door, and everybody
NOTE CONF
who has access to them, they also need to be
checked.
NOTE CONF
Why did it take 2030 years for people to realize
that?
NOTE CONF
Oh my God, right?
That's because, again, security is not a strategy subject, it's
NOTE CONF
a technology subject, and it takes decades for industry to
learn simple things like that, yeah.
NOTE CONF
And I blame it on people like us because we
have been pumping security people into the industry from engineering
NOTE CONF
who have no business background or no strategy background, and
they're pure technology and they're expected to do strategic things
NOTE CONF
without a strategic background.
So there's all these reasons why these organizations get attacked.
NOTE CONF
I think for critical infrastructure, they are the most, you
know, they are the most risk, uh, well, the most
NOTE CONF
exposed, right?
So your, your electricity, your telcos, your, well, actually your
NOTE CONF
banks, your water, all of them are exposed to nation-based
attacks because if you want to bring down a country,
NOTE CONF
which sector do you hit first?
Easy question.
NOTE CONF
Sorry?
No electricity.
NOTE CONF
Right, you bring down the whole country, you want to
bring it down, you hit electricity, and everybody depends on
NOTE CONF
electricity.
Within a day, telcos are down, telecommunications runs on electricity,
NOTE CONF
banking is down, right?
Name it, any sector you can think of.
NOTE CONF
Everybody within 48 hours, everybody's down, even gas is down
because gas turbines start up on electrical impulses as well.
NOTE CONF
So other than oil, which is the only other source
of energy you have, which can't run everything, you're pretty
NOTE CONF
much down if electricity is down.
And what about water?
NOTE CONF
Nobody talks about water getting hit, right?
Water gets hit and there's no water.
NOTE CONF
How long do you think we have, you know, not
long, but water doesn't spend money on cyber at all,
NOTE CONF
even though water turbines and so forth, they are now
cyber controlled, right?
NOTE CONF
Scata systems, but nobody talks about water because nobody wants
to talk about water because water doesn't have any money
NOTE CONF
to spend on cyber.
Banks and telcos have money, right?
NOTE CONF
So somehow water is not a problem, but if you
look at the risk exposure, water is hugely, hugely exposed.
NOTE CONF
Yeah.
Nobody wants to talk about it.
NOTE CONF
OK, confidentiality.
3, confidentiality, integrity, availability.
NOTE CONF
When I say CIA I mean confidentiality, integrity, availability, not
central intelligence agency.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Very quickly, you guys, this is so intuitive.
NOTE CONF
This is a confidentiality attack.
I send an email to you and the third party
NOTE CONF
copies it.
That's a confidentiality attack.
NOTE CONF
This is a very simple illustration of a message comes
from the source, goes to the destination, and the third
NOTE CONF
party intercepts it.
That interception is a, there should be an arrow here,
NOTE CONF
sorry, I don't know why there's no arrow there.
Um, that's a confidentiality attack.
NOTE CONF
An integrity attack looks like this.
So.
NOTE CONF
Goes to the unauthorized party.
The unauthorized party takes the intercepts the message, stops the
NOTE CONF
message from going to the destination, changes the message, then
relays the message to the intended destination, and the destination
NOTE CONF
does not realize that the message was changed on the
route.
NOTE CONF
Yeah, that's an, that's an integrity attack.
And then availability attack is basically when you disrupt.
NOTE CONF
A service, right?
And there's two types of availability attacks, one, which is
NOTE CONF
a temporary disruption, and one which is total destruction.
There's two levels, one is a temporary availability and one
NOTE CONF
is a permanent availability attack.
OK.
NOTE CONF
What we're going to go into detail with, with controls
because the whole subject is about controls, but there are
NOTE CONF
3 categories of controls.
There are prescriptive controls like your strategy, your risk, your
NOTE CONF
policy.
There are suggestive controls like your training, education, awareness, and
NOTE CONF
there's technological controls, which is your firewalls, intrusion detection systems,
antivirus, anti-malware, all those sorts of things, and they are
NOTE CONF
interdependent for them to work, they need to work together.
OK.
NOTE CONF
What is the role of information security?
What does it do for your firm?
NOTE CONF
It does a lot of things, but primarily it allows
your company to actually function because without security nothing is
NOTE CONF
going to function.
That's at an abstract level.
NOTE CONF
But more specifically, when you buy an application, it comes
with vulnerabilities, so it protects the application from being attacked
NOTE CONF
and it protects you from the application.
Right, so every application has vulnerabilities, and that is a
NOTE CONF
conduit or a pathway into your firm.
So you need to be very careful when you buy
NOTE CONF
an application and bring it into your trusted environment because
it can be the reason why you get attacked.
NOTE CONF
It protects your data, information and knowledge.
We already talked about that to some extent, and it
NOTE CONF
protects your technology assets as well, makes sure that they
are functioning.
NOTE CONF
Nobody walks in, picks up your server, and walks out.
Which has happened before in Australian government before.
NOTE CONF
OK, now, I have about 10 minutes.
Very important survey.
NOTE CONF
So 21, 22, not too long ago, five years.
I know it's a bit of time, but these surveys
NOTE CONF
aren't aren't done very often.
When they're done well, they're really worth talking about, so.
NOTE CONF
This survey looked at chief information security officers.
Now, the Chief Information Security Officer is the highest ranking
NOTE CONF
individual in an organization whose primary responsibility is security.
So for us, they're a bit of a proxy for
NOTE CONF
the organization.
By proxy, I mean they represent the whole enterprise because
NOTE CONF
they are responsible for the whole enterprise.
So if we want to understand how the organization behaves
NOTE CONF
around security, looking at the CISO is a very good
mirror, a very good source of information for us.
NOTE CONF
This particular survey looked at organizations that had, um, there's
a bit of a U curve.
NOTE CONF
A lot of people or very little people, right?
So there was not a whole lot of consistency in
NOTE CONF
their data set, but they did get a lot of
global multinational firms and SISOs at that level, which makes
NOTE CONF
this really interesting.
Um, and they've got some statistics which you can look
NOTE CONF
at in your notes, you can look at them in
a while.
NOTE CONF
Um, which industries have SISOs?
This is very interesting.
NOTE CONF
So banking, telcos, energy tend to have SISOs.
But small enterprise tend not to have SISOs for obvious
NOTE CONF
reasons, right?
They can't afford them.
NOTE CONF
But also there are certain types of companies like transport
that don't have SISOs for some reason.
NOTE CONF
So not all sectors have chief information security officers.
You're almost certainly going to find them in heavily regulated
NOTE CONF
sectors like banking, right, very heavily regulated, always going to
have a SISO.
NOTE CONF
Telcos, not as regulated, but still will have SISOs, yeah.
And then very large multinational companies, oil will have usually
NOTE CONF
sIOs, but retail sometimes won't have sIOs.
Transport might not have water, might not have a lot
NOTE CONF
of these other gas might not have sizes.
Um.
NOTE CONF
Career path wise, it's very interesting to see that most
ISOs come from an IT or software engineering.
NOTE CONF
Background.
So you don't have the situation where somebody has a
NOTE CONF
business background and they become a CISO.
They usually have an engineering and IT background and they
NOTE CONF
become a CISO, OK.
That's important to understand because it means that the person
NOTE CONF
in charge of security has a very technology-centered view, right?
So no law enforcement, no secret service, no army, right?
NOTE CONF
Civilian, technology or engineering.
Right.
NOTE CONF
And this tells you so much about, about the cyber
defensive ability of the firm, right?
NOTE CONF
They are not military people, so they have no understanding
of warfare, even though cyber is part business, part warfare,
NOTE CONF
right?
They are not business people, so they don't understand the
NOTE CONF
business.
All they are tech people, right?
NOTE CONF
And when they get elevated to that level, they become
a problem, right?
NOTE CONF
Because at that strategic level, the tech person is still
speaking tech, as if they're at the operational level.
NOTE CONF
And they can't speak to the business, and they can't
speak to the leadership, and nobody understands what they're doing.
NOTE CONF
Now, I know this is a bit of an extreme,
you know, uh, description of it, but there's really good
NOTE CONF
research out of MIT that shows the business IT disconnect,
and we see it every day whenever we do case
NOTE CONF
studies in banks.
OK.
NOTE CONF
Um, the other on the right hand side, really interesting
to see what was the last job of every CISO
NOTE CONF
they, they interviewed?
And what was it?
NOTE CONF
CISO.
So, what does that tell us?
NOTE CONF
It means that if you're a CISO today, you're probably
gonna be a CISO tomorrow, and that if you're gonna
NOTE CONF
be a CISO tomorrow, you probably retire as a CISO,
which means there is no way you're, you're gonna get
NOTE CONF
basically stuck in this job, and you're not gonna be
able to get out of it, right?
NOTE CONF
Now, there's some data to say CISO CIO where the
CIO is the ceiling, but CISO CFO.
NOTE CONF
Impossible, or almost impossible.
SaiO, CEO unless it's a tech firm, impossible.
NOTE CONF
Right?
That tells you so much.
NOTE CONF
The most sorry yeah CISO CEO impossible or CTO yeah
yeah CTO again possible but CTO you would argue isn't
NOTE CONF
the promotion.
Right?
NOTE CONF
So you go laterally.
Yeah, so the most powerful person in the firm is?
NOTE CONF
The CEO, then the CFO, then the COO, and then
a number of other C-suites.
NOTE CONF
Not including, so there was a really interesting survey that
asked CFOs and CIOs.
NOTE CONF
They asked CFOs, do you think a CIO is a
C-suite executive?
NOTE CONF
And they asked the CIO, do you think you're a
C-suite executive?
NOTE CONF
Every CIO said, I'm a C-suite executive.
Every CFO said the CIO is not a C-suite executive.
NOTE CONF
So that tells you in the firm there is an
inner circle and an inner inner circle.
NOTE CONF
Even with that C-suite title, they're just IT managers.
That's how the business side sees them because the business
NOTE CONF
is a revenue generator and IT is a cost center.
That's right.
NOTE CONF
That's how it plays out.
The primary role of the CISO, here is a number
NOTE CONF
of roles.
Security operations, governance risk compliance, penetration testing, security architecture, brought,
NOTE CONF
I mean, a lot of these are operational.
There's some strategic, but sort of middle management level.
NOTE CONF
I'm not, I don't have time to go through this,
but you can stare at this.
NOTE CONF
If you want to understand what are the things that
ASISO does, here's the full breadth of it.
NOTE CONF
Right, a lot of operational work.
What is the most significant cyber risk that they talk
NOTE CONF
about?
Ransomware.
NOTE CONF
Insider threats.
It's not entirely surprising for me that they're all technology
NOTE CONF
based.
The technology person is mirroring back to you the technology
NOTE CONF
risks.
I'm worried about technology things.
NOTE CONF
Are you worried about a physical document going astray?
I wouldn't have a clue, right?
NOTE CONF
They're not talking about it at all.
This is not unexpected.
NOTE CONF
But very scary.
Who do they report to?
NOTE CONF
Almost always, the CIO, CISO to CIO.
So you want to know how, how much power somebody
NOTE CONF
has, you look at how many people they have to
report to before they get to the CEO.
NOTE CONF
Right?
So if you've got two handshakes, CISO to CIO, CIO
NOTE CONF
to CEO, that means you're less powerful than if you
were CISO to CEO.
NOTE CONF
Right?
It's power, it's just pure power.
NOTE CONF
If you were CEO, CIO, group CIO, group CIO, CISO,
you could be buried 4 levels down or 5 levels
NOTE CONF
down in the firm.
How much power do you have there?
NOTE CONF
Very little power.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
Why am I talking power?
Because power is decision making, right?
NOTE CONF
When a decision needs to be made, who's got the
power to make it?
NOTE CONF
That's how you measure your ability to influence things in
your firm.
NOTE CONF
How often do you, how often do these CISOs report
to their board?
NOTE CONF
Quarterly at best.
6 monthly, sometimes yearly.
NOTE CONF
That means the board does not see the size so
except once a year.
NOTE CONF
Can you imagine what that means?
Just, just, just think about that for a moment.
NOTE CONF
If you don't understand what a board does, a board,
let me give you an analogy.
NOTE CONF
Take a sports team, like a soccer team, right?
The board is the owner of the soccer team.
NOTE CONF
The coach is the CEO, right?
The job of the CEO or the coach is to
NOTE CONF
select players and to run all the plays on the
pitch.
NOTE CONF
The board does not get involved in what's going on
on the pitch.
NOTE CONF
The board's only job is to appoint the coach.
Right, they appoint the CEO and they can sniff around
NOTE CONF
on the pitch to see whether the, what the coach
is telling them is true.
NOTE CONF
So the board is like an owner, but they don't
get involved in the business.
NOTE CONF
They create the guardrails within which the business operates.
They have fiduciary responsibilities to make sure that the company
NOTE CONF
is going in the right direction, but if it's not
going in the right direction, their major lever is fire
NOTE CONF
the CEO and appoint a new one.
They don't appoint SISOs.
NOTE CONF
They don't appoint CIOs, they appoint the CEO.
OK, that's the role of the board.
NOTE CONF
So, if the board, who is ultimately responsible for the
firm, sees the CISO once a year, It suggests that
NOTE CONF
they're thinking about the security of the firm once a
year.
NOTE CONF
That's how important cybersecurity is for the firm.
What is the thing that keeps Asao up at night?
NOTE CONF
Stress.
Related to my job.
NOTE CONF
see.
Right?
NOTE CONF
Burnout, stress.
The market, job loss as a breach, right?
NOTE CONF
It's a thankless job because if there's a major cyber
incident, who's going to be responsible?
NOTE CONF
You are, yo, you're responsible for it, right?
Even if it was not your fault, you're the person
NOTE CONF
who's gonna get fired for it.
What's the next role that you would like to do?
NOTE CONF
I would love to be a board member.
So, over 90% of CISOs hope to improve alignment between
NOTE CONF
security and business, but 46%, nearly half, fear the inability
to accomplish that, right?
NOTE CONF
Only 22% of respondents work in an organization where the
CISO reports directly to the CEO.
NOTE CONF
40% still report to the CIO.
Only 18% of CISOs have held managerial roles before moving
NOTE CONF
into the organization.
Oh my God, never been a manager before.
NOTE CONF
18% have been a manager before.
That means almost all the people in security management have
NOTE CONF
no prior management experience.
So here are some questions that you might want to
NOTE CONF
think about.
What factors are likely to derail your attempt at trying
NOTE CONF
to improve your relationship with the business?
Why do you think CISOs, the report to CEOs are
NOTE CONF
so low?
Why do you think only 18% of CISOs have previously
NOTE CONF
held managerial roles?
What are the main tasks and responsibilities of the CISOs?
NOTE CONF
And for your next week's question, What are the 3
types?
NOTE CONF
Of strategic cyber risks faced by an organization.
OK.
NOTE CONF
The key word is strategic.
If you were to go to the CEOO and say,
NOTE CONF
sir, what is your single most important cybersecurity risk?
It would be one of these 3.
NOTE CONF
I'll see you next week.
OK.
NOTE CONF
outside.
Actually, no, there's no press after us.
NOTE CONF
We should be OK.
Uh, so you talk about the 3 different types of
NOTE CONF
cyber attacks.
Sorry, uh, you talk about the 3 climates.
NOTE CONF
3 types of cyber attacks.
Are you confidentiality, yeah, yeah, yeah.
NOTE CONF
What man.
Oh, that's, no, no, no, these are, so it's not
NOTE CONF
about being Trump.
It's about.
NOTE CONF
We've got a document.
Oh, I see, I see.
NOTE CONF
the story obviously if I if I.
Yeah.
NOTE CONF
I I will, I will release it on the weekend,
right, so I have not released the the presentation details.
NOTE CONF
It hasn't come out yet, the weekend, so don't have
to cheaters yet.
NOTE CONF
Thank you.
No, you show up.
NOTE CONF
I, I wear it.
It's in my slides, and you will get it when
NOTE CONF
you come to the actual.
It.
NOTE CONF
I It No, no, come to the to the actual
6 people, but again, we'll release everything in this on
NOTE CONF
the weekend.
Yeah, we'll release.
NOTE CONF
Yes, yeah, presentation is in week 5.
OK, thank you.
NOTE CONF
I.
I so I just started like.
NOTE CONF
I haven't.
I'm really interested in.
NOTE CONF
I wouldn't say that.
I wouldn't say that because all the stats most of
NOTE CONF
them have.
My thing is open your mind, especially in the subject
NOTE CONF
you learn in the management and you probably see some
people with African background.
NOTE CONF